本影音版权属其出版、发行方，字幕制作仅供学术交流之用 请于下载后24小时内删除，并不得有公开传播或作商业盈利之行为 若有违法等相关行为，诸神字幕组恕不承担任何法律或连带责任。
おう　ガモ　飲みの誘いか
Oh, Gamo, you looking for a drinking partner?
妙な気を起こさないか　見回りに来ただけだ
I just came to make sure you
don't try anything funny.
翻译 koki  放 晴  La Fatalité
代行が見つかるまで精精おとなしくしてろ
Just try to stay quiet until we
find the Acting Director.
はいはい
Yes, sir.
お前はすっかり代行の右腕に収まっちまったからなあ
You have fallen into the role of
her right hand man, after all.
压制 暗之亚瑟王  校对 凉YAN Lucifer 时间 Lucifer
プレイボーイの哀れな末路だ
A sad fate for a playboy like yourself.
哀れなか
Sad, huh?
Mattalast.
マット＝アラストか
あなたを止めに来たんですよ
I've come to stop you.
An ex-thief named Minth recently
became an apprentice.
この間見習いになったミンスと言う元盗賊
彼の能力が「聖浄眼」っと言いましてね
They say his ability is the Sacred Eyes.
確か人の魂を見ると
Which he can use to peer into people's souls.
えー　やつがあなたを見たんですよ
Yes. He looked at yours.
He said the Acting Director
has quite a sizeable plan.
代行が何か重大の決意を抱えていると
やー　驚きましたよ
I was surprised, actually. Who'd have thought...
まさか　天国に刃向かおうとしているとは
you'd try to rebel against Heaven.
I'd hate to dirty the Library...
図書館内は汚せませんのでね
俺を殺すか
You're going to try and kill me?
On the next Acting Director's orders,
I can't go quite that far.
次期代行の命令して　殺すまではしませんよ
次期代行か
The next Acting Director?
お前がここまで職務に忠実になったのは
Is your new-found fervor for your duties
ハミュッツ＝メセタへの感情ゆえか
coming from your feelings
towards Hamyuts Meseta?
Would you stop that?
やめてくださいよ
I merely feel compelled to do so upon learning
the truth behind the Armed Librarians.
武装司書の真実を知ってしまったからには
従わざるを得ない
それだけです
That's all it is.
You may have learned the truth
behind the Armed Librarians,
君は　武装司書の真実を知っていても
ハミュッツの真実は知らない
but you don't know the truth behind Hamyuts.
I hate having long conversations
when I'm sober.
酒が入らないところで　長話もなんでしない
早いところ終わりにさせてもらいます
I think I'll get this out of the way now.
ハミュッツをいくら思ったところで
No matter the gravity of your
feelings towards Hamyuts...
Farewell, Fotona.
さよなら　フォトナさん
...you'll be left with nothing.
君には何も残らない
さよなら
Farewell.
何も残らない…か
Left with nothing, huh?
The truth behind Heaven...
The Armed Librarians'secret...
天国の正体　武装司書の秘密
全てを理解しても　今も分からない謎が一つ
Knowing even those, there is still
one mystery I cannot crack.
Hamy, who are you?
ハミ　お前は誰なんだ
诸
神字幕组
剥がれ落ちた夢 澱む幻
Hagare ochita yume yodomu maboroshi
もう この世界を見放した者さえ
Mou kono sekai wo mihanashita
mono sae tsutsumi komu kotoba
包み込む言葉
刹那に消えゆく
Setsuna ni kieyuku
共に囚われの明日を取り戻そう
Tomo ni toraware no ashita wo torimodosou
何もかも失くしても
Nani mo kamo nakushite mo
最期の審議の日まで　ずっと
Saigo no shingi no hi made
Zutto hana no you ni tsuyoku sakihokore
花のように強く咲き誇れ
絶望のオト　拾い集めて
Zetsubou no oto hiroi atsumete
永久に奏でる　ストレインに変える
Towa ni kanaderu sutorein ni kaeru
僅かなヒカリ　すがりついても
Wazukana hikari sugaritsuitemo todomaru kara
留まるから
届けたい　残らず
Todoketai nokorazu
第24话 真实
与
Episode 24
Truth, Love, and the Second Sealed Library
爱恋
和
第二封印书库
What the heck?
なんじゃ
離れなさい　ミンス
Get away from her, Minth!
Love me... Please love me!
愛して　チャコリーを愛して
Sir?
顧問
What happened to me?
わしは…
チャコリーに焦がれちゃって　焦がれちゃって
You desired Chacoly so badly
that you forgot yourself?
我を忘れたって
That is Chacoly's special ability:
Soul Transference.
これこそがチャコリーの能力
「心魂共有」
Soul Transference?
「心魂共有」？
It's a superior version of Milepoc's telepathy.
ミレポの「思考共有」能力の上位版よ
More than merely communicating thoughts,
考えていることをやり取りするだけじゃなく
she is able to read the other's emotions
相手の感情を読み取り　そして感情を与えることができる
as well as implant emotions into them.
If Chacoly feels sad, your heart will weep.
チャコリーが悲しめば悲しまざるを得なくなる
If Chacoly wishes for something,
your heart will desire it.
チャコリーが望めば望まざるを得なくなる
Your actual emotions don't factor in at all.
こっちの感情なんてお構いなしのね
That old man, Makia...
あの爺　マキアは　この能力を使って
He used her ability to try and make a
certain man fall in love with Chacoly.
ある男にチャコリーを愛させようとした
In order to save that man from despair.
その男を絶望から救うためにね
Hamy... love...
はな…して
Chacoly, you...
チャコリー　あんた…
Hamy... love... me... too...
ハミ　チャコリーを愛して
チャコリー　あたし…
Chacoly, I...
Acting Director!
代行
Hamy... love... me...
ハミ　愛…して
Chacoly... I...
あたしは　あんたが…
... love...
愛…
I...
あんたが…
大嫌いよ
hate you.
ラスコール
Lascall...
No, the war-machine of the past,
the stone sword of spent time, Yor...
いいえ　追憶の戦記の一つ　「過ぎ去りし石剣ヨル」
You're here, aren't you?
いるんでしょう
随分と大活躍じゃない
You've been busy lately, huh?
恐れ入ります
Pardon me.
Hey, how does it feel when you
turn someone into a book?
ねえ　人を「本」にする時ってどんな感じなの
Do you get all tingly?
ぞくぞくしちゃう？
I am nothing more than a stone sword.
私はただの石剣です　そこに快楽などございません
I take no pleasure from it.
Although,
ただ　私には人間という存在が
I do think it must be quite fun to be human.
とても楽しいもののように思えます
Quite fun, huh?
楽しいもの　ねえ
Acting Director...
代行
Help me, will ya?
手伝ってちょうだい
When was it?
何時だったかなあ
I peered into the Acting Director's
soul once, out of curiosity.
好奇心から代行を「聖浄眼」で見たことがあったんじゃ
"Her dominant trait is villainy."
相は凶悪　思考は邪悪　望みは血みどろの大虐殺
"Her thoughts are of evil."
"She wishes for bloodstained holocaust."
...is what I expected it to be.
そんなところじゃろうと思っての
私でも想像が付きますね
I would picture the same.
However, I began to doubt my ability...
じゃがな
自分の能力に疑いが感じてしまってのは
I stopped thinking about scanning her again.
それ以降は代行を見てみようなんぞ考えるのはやめた
どんな相が出ていたのですか
What were her actual traits?
Her dominant trait is self-loathing.
相は自虐　思考は空白　望みは愛
Her thoughts are void.
She wishes for... love.
Chacoly, let me take a look at how
you've lived since we split up.
チャコリー
あたしと別れてからのあんたの人生　見させてもらうわ
Say, are you the Acting Director?
ねえ　館長代行ってあなた？
チャコリーをルルタのところまで案内してほしいの
I'd like you to take me to see Ruruta.
Take... Chacoly...
チャコリー
やっと会えるね　ルルタ
Ruruta and I can finally meet.
Ruruta Coozancoona.
ルルタ＝クーザンクーナ
Who is it?
誰だ
チャコリー＝ココット　だよ
Chacoly Cocotte.
Forty years ago, I asked Makia Dexiart to kill me.
僕は40年前　マキア＝デキシアートに僕自身の殺害を依頼した
Did he create you?
彼が君を作り上げたのか
He did.
そうだよ
My weakness overcame me that day.
My weakness was exposed for all to see.
あの日　僕は弱い自分に屈し
弱い自分を曝け出してしまった
I've long wanted to erase that
day's shameful deed.
ずっと　あの日の醜態を消したくてたまらなかった
You're being silly, Ruruta.
ルルタは馬鹿のことを言ってる
ルルタはチャコリーを待っていたの
You've been waiting for me
for two-thousand years.
二千年の間
The reason you exist is so you can love me.
チャコリーと愛し合うために　ルルタの人生はあったんだよ
Let... Let me... go.
は…はな…せ
Tell me, Ruruta... Do you love me?
ねえ　ルルタ　チャコリーが好き？
殺…したい　心の底から
I want... to kill you...
from the bottom of my heart...
Denied. You have to love me!
否定　ルルタはチャコリーを愛さなきゃだめ
Love... you?
チャコリーを　愛を
So, Ruruta, will you die with me?
ねえ　ルルタ
チャコリーと一緒に死のう　延々に一つになろう
Let's remain as one forever!
否定するよ　だめだよ
Sorry, I can't let you do that.
You're going to die with me.
ルルタはチャコリーと一緒に死ぬの
What gives? How are you able to resist me?
なんで　どうして抵抗できるの
Aren't I your everything? Aren't I?
チャコリーだけがあなたのすべて　そうでしょう
Nie...
ニ…
何？
What?
ニーニウ
Nieniu...
ニーニウ　誰　それ
Nieniu? Who's that?
Fine. If you won't tell me,
I'll just read your soul.
いいよ　答えないなら
読んであげるよ　ルルタの心
何　この歌
What song is this?
なんで　ルルタがチャコリーじゃない女と
What?! How can you be with another girl?!
だって　チャコリーはルルタと死ぬ　そのためだけに
But we're supposed to die together!
That's the only reason I...
やめて　やめて
Make it stop...
Make it stop!
Oh? So that was the cause of Ruruta's despair.
ふうん　これがルルタの絶望だったの
He's nothing but a baby.
ただの甘ちゃんじゃない
あたしらはこんなやつに熱を上げ続けてたったわけね
And we exerted all that energy over him...
Okay, this is where we go
our separate ways.
じゃあ　ここでお別れだね
Chacoly, you cannot let anyone
know about my abilities.
チャコリー　私の能力　絶対ばらしちゃだめだから
Who am I gonna tell?
別に言わないよ
それにハミなんて　チャコリーがルルタと死んだらもう用なし
Besides, you won't be needed
once I die with Ruruta.
あんたは　私から生きる意味まで奪うつもり？
Are you gonna try and steal
my reason for living?
What am I supposed to do if Ruruta goes away?
ルルタがいなくなったら　私はどうすればいい
Well, you could maybe... I know!
ハミは　そうだね
You could fall in love and get married,
like a normal person.
普通の相手に普通に恋をして　普通の結婚をするの
Say what?
なにそれ
Then, your family will care for you and watch
as you go, with tearful eyes. So lame!
それでね　家族に見守られて涙なんか流される
ださい死に方するの
Everyone will be like, "No, don't die!"
And then you die.
皆に死んでほしくないって思われて　そうやって死ぬんだよ
Bye.
じゃあね
Chacoly.
チャコリー
Since this is goodbye, I'll let you
read my soul, just this once.
最後に一度だけ　私の心読んでもいいわよ
ハミになんて興味ないよ
Not interested.
You were such a little brat.
あんたは本当に糞ったれだった
I didn't kill you in the fortress because you
kept me entertained for all those years.
あんたをあの砦で殺さなかったのは　長年の憂さ晴らしのため…って
But...
Do you know why your Soul Transference
didn't work on me earlier?
どうしてさっき
あんたの「心魂共有」能力があたしに通じなかったか分かる？
Love... me...
チャコリーを愛して
Because I always loved you.
最初から愛してたのよ
You little brat, Chacoly.
糞ったれのチャコリーをね
Over the course of all those years,
being brought up as a tool to kill Ruruta,
ルルタを殺す道具として育てられた長い長い日々の中で
you were my only friend.
あんただけがあたしの友だちだった
However, I will be the one who kills Ruruta.
でもね　ルルタを殺すのはあたし
A peaceful, warm, and lame death
is no longer allowed for me.
穏やかで暖かなださい死に方なんて
あたしにはもう許されない
"I am sick and tired of years of waiting"
飽き果てた　待ち続ける日々の長さとこの世界に生きるすべての人に
"and all the living beings in this world."
Where's Rithly?
リズリーさんは
Out looking for the Acting Director.
代行探しの方に回ってる
What? So we're the only ones
guarding the Library?
ええ　じゃ　ここの守りは俺たちだけ…
Letting apprentices stand guard?
見習いに見張りをさせるとは
Looks like things have gotten
pretty chaotic around here.
よほど混乱していると見える
One must know Heaven to destroy Heaven.
天国を滅ぼすためには　まず天国を知らねば
To do that...
そのためには…
おかしい　武装司書らはともかく
This is strange. I can understand the
Armed Librarians not being here,
衛獣はどうした
but where are the Guardian Beasts?
This... is Heaven?
これが…天国
So this is Heaven. That makes this...
これが天国　そしてこれが…
Ruruta Coozancoona.
ルルタ＝クーザンクーナ
Mattalast?
マット＝アラスト
You probably came down here to crash
the Armed Librarians' party.
武装司書パーティをねらい　地下に潜ろうとしたんだろうが
Seems your plan has failed, Enlike.
予定が狂ったな　エンリケ
Because Hamyuts decided to escape,
the net result is the same.
ハミュッツが逃亡してくれたおかげで
同じような効果が生まれた
問題は何もない
There is no problem here.
The fact you know about this is a problem.
知られたからには　というやつだ
This way, Rithly!
こっちです　リズリーさん
What the hell, man? An intruder?
なんだよ　もう侵入者って
第五階層ぐらい　お前らだけで守っとけって…
You guys should be able to at
least handle the fifth floor...
Ow...
なんだよ
What the heck?
おい　死んでるじゃ…
Hey! This guy is dead...
ど、どうして象兵が…
Wh-What's an Elephant Guard doing here?
第四階層にしか出てこないはずじゃんか
They aren't supposed to go
higher than the fourth labyrinth.
Everyone, return at once!
緊急召集　地下迷宮で衛獣が暴れ出しました
Guardian Beasts are loose in
the underground labyrinths.
すべての武装司書が図書迷宮に向かってください
All Armed Librarians, head
to the Library's labyrinth.
A Guardian Beast?
衛獣？
悲しい…よ
I am... sad.
今の声は…
That voice...
So very... sad.
とても　悲しい
Damn! The next two seconds,
だめだ　次の二秒後も
次も　次も　次も　次も
and the next, and next, and next, and next!
悲しいよ
I am sad.
はーい　皆さん　お久し振り
Hi, guys. How's everyone doing?
Hamy?
ハミ
うんっ　ええーと
So, um,
今君たちが戦っているのは「終章の獣」という存在です
the beasts you are fighting are known
as the "Beasts of the Final Chapter."
待って
Wait!
Long ago, at the Age of Paradise's end,
遥か昔　楽園時代の終わり
未来管理者オルントーラによって生み出された殲滅兵器です
the overseer of life that is yet to come, Orntorra,
brought them into being as weapons
of mass destruction.
They've been known as
Guardian Beasts ever since.
それをずっと「衛獣」という名で読んでいましたね
We told you they are the
guardians of the labyrinths
過去管理者バントーラが生み出した迷宮の守護者と伝えていました
that Bantorra, the overseer of life
that has passed, created.
But it's all a bunch of lies.
ですが　それは嘘っぱちです
嘘っぱちだ？
A bunch of lies?!
Yep. A bunch of lies.
そう　嘘っぱち
All Acting Directors, myself included,
have lied to you all along.
あたしを含めて　歴代の館長代行はあなたたちに嘘をついてきました
Tons and tons of big fat lies.
大変に大変に　たくさんの嘘を
ここでまずは　重大な発表をしましょう
Now, I have a huge announcement for you all.
Ruruta Coozancoona, Director of the great
Bantorra Library, which we call home,
我らが偉大なるバントーラ図書館館長ルルタ＝クーザンクーナが
本日を持ちまして図書館の閉館を決定しました
has decided to close the Library as of today.
Wh-Who the heck is that?
な、何者だ　それは
ルルタ＝クーザンクーナ
Ruruta Coozancoona.
この図書館の創立者　過去神バントーラを蹴落とし
The man who ousted the Library's founder,
the God of the past, Bantorra,
図書館館長になった人物です
to become the Director of the Library.
ハミ
Hamy...
皆さん　長らくのお勤め本当にお疲れ様でした
Everyone, I thank you kindly
for your years of service.
バントーラ図書館は　武装司書は　今日で終わりです
Today signifies the end of Bantorra
Library and the Armed Librarians.
It all ends today.
今日で　終わりです
I will not allow you to die amidst such pain.
苦しみの中で死なせはしない
長い間　僕のために　生きてくれた
You've lived many years for my sake.
This is the one gift I can give to you.
君たちへの　唯一の贈り物
The Tearless Ending.
涙なき　結末の力
Sure is hot again today, huh, Kayz?
今日も暑いですね　刑事さん
息子さんからですよ
You have a letter from your son.
Huh? Snow?
あれ　雪　どうして
But why?
「終章の獣」が目覚めた世界に
The Tearless Ending
涙なき結末の力が降り注ぐ
falls upon a world in which the Beasts
of the Final Chapter have awakened.
すべての生きとし生けるものは　深い眠りにつく
All living beings will fall into a deep slumber,
二度と朝が来ることはない　永遠の眠りに
an eternal slumber where the
morn shall never return.
The tale of those who guide the world
to its ruin and those who resist...
世界の終末を導く者と　それに抗う者の物語
私はただ　物語の行きつく先を見たかっただけ
I just wanted to see how such a tale ends.
However,
ですが　なんと静かな大団円
such a tranquil grand finale
いささか　叙情的すぎる
somehow seems overly poetic.
Is this...
これは　このまま…終わって…しま…のか
Is this how... it all ends?
俺は　終われんない
I refuse to die!
Say, Matt?
ねえ　マット
うん？
Hmm?
もしあたしを殺せる人誰もいなくなったら
If no one out there can kill me,
マット殺してくれる
will you do it, Matt?
You're okay with that?
いいのか
ふん　あたしねえ　マットにだけは殺されたくない
You're the only person by whose
hands I don't want to die.
The only one...
それだけは　いやなの
I will not allow another man to
be the one who kills Hamy.
ハミを　他の男に殺させるわけにはいかない
Mattalast...
マット=アラスト
I haven't made coffee in a while,
but this came out pretty good.
久しぶりだったけど　上手に入れられたわね
It would be a shame if the last cup of
coffee had in the world were lousy.
この世で最後のコーヒーがまずかったら最悪だったわ
All Ireia ever made was black tea.
イレイアのお婆ちゃんが入れるのは　紅茶ばっかりだった
Your room is the only place I can drink coffee.
コーヒーが飲めるのはあんたの部屋でだけ
Black tea during the week and
coffee on our days off...
平日には紅茶を飲んで　休日にはコーヒーを飲んで
Wasting my days away with the Armed
Librarians, who couldn't be ruthless if they tried.
残酷に成り切れない人のいい武装司書のやつらと
無益な日々を過ごして
ルルタを殺すためだけに生きてきたはずのあたしが
Considering my entire life was
designed merely to kill Ruruta,
少しだけ　このままでいいかって　思えちゃったのよね
I sort of thought it'd be nice to
stay like this for a while.
Ruruta Coozancoona.
ルルタ＝クーザンクーナ
Tobu hane yume toraete
Tobu mane yami oyoideru
Aoku kanashii sora ni kotae kiite miyou
Shimaru tobira tataita (tsuyoku)
Nukedashite saigo no aisatsu
Dare wo sagashi tsuzuketa no to
Koe wo ubawareru dake de wakaranai
Oreta ai no seide
Nanimokamo nakushita ima
Tenshi wa mou konai
Dominant Space
空ろな空から降り積もるは
The Tearless Ending
Tranquility,
涙なき結末の力
falls from a blank sky.
気まぐれな救世主の情けに抱かれて
In the arms of your capricious savior's mercy,
Tranquility, Indolence,
世界を　静かに眠れ
rest in peace, sweet world.
静寂与懒觉和绝望的故事
Tranquility, Indolence, and a Tale of Despair
rest in peace, sweet world.